You're going to tell me the first thing
that comes to your mind. Vladimir Putin.
>> [snorts]
[laughter]
>> But there's there is something right now
going on in the Middle East. Obviously,
there's a war there.
And it's it's politics are seeping into
American foreign policy in the current
American administration. And I mean
specifically Zionism. That idea. And
there are now Christian groups that are
picking up this idea of Zionism and
making it um
trying to make it biblical and
biblically sound.
>> it's not.
>> And it's not.
>> There's literally nothing in scripture
to support Zionism. Nothing.
>> I would argue it's it's theology is
anti-orthodox because it
>> I would agree without any reservation.
>> Yeah.
The way it negatively impacts the people
in the Middle East, right? And how have
you seen that really
in your time there?
>> You know, in the not too distant past,
Palestine used to be 10% Christian.
And now almost all of those Christians
live in Michigan.
Because they were forced out.
>> Yeah.
>> What the Israeli government has done
in Palestine,
not just to Christians, but to the
Muslims as well, is literally the
definition of ethnic cleansing. You
force people out of their ancestral land
and just take it by force.
Uh we see it every day, literally every
day in the West Bank. We see it in Gaza.
But this conflict
in Gaza has brought out the worst, I
think, in the Israelis. You know, when
24 women and children
take refuge in St. Porphyrios Church in
Gaza, the oldest continuously operating
church on the planet,
and the Israelis then bomb it using
fighter jets, killing all 24 women and
children. We've got a problem.
I don't understand how these poor,
deluded, misguided American evangelicals
think that supporting Zionism
is somehow supporting Christ and
Christianity. It's anti-Christian. I saw
an Orthodox priest um on a podcast a
couple of days ago
saying that
it is Israel that is the Antichrist.
Right? Because what is an Antichrist? An
Antichrist is someone who acts in
opposition to the teachings of the
Christ.
It's that simple. It's not a guy with
horns and a 666 on his head.
It's people acting in opposition to
Christianity, the teachings of Christ.
And we're seeing it every day in the
West Bank and Gaza Strip.
>> Sure. On the kind of the topic of the
government kind of pushing stuff, um
in a lot of our circles, we have a lot
of people who are really interested in
uh kind of like Western propaganda in
movies and things like that. So, in your
time uh at the CIA, did you kind of see
that propaganda machine at work uh
actively?
>> Every day.
>> What kind of stuff?
>> There's even a word for it. It's called
active measures.
Yeah. It can be something as stupid
as
a pirate radio station
in Yemen playing jazz
so that young Yemeni men will say, "Wow,
what cool music. That makes me want to
be pro-American."
That was actually
>> Wow.
>> an operation. Yeah. Um so, yeah, you see
it every single day. And 99 times out of
100, it's a stupid idea.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you see it in like CIA like sorry, uh
Hollywood movies that come out today?
>> gosh, yes. This is something that the
CIA was late to to the game with.
Starting in the late 1930s, the FBI
forged this uh
relationship with Hollywood so that
literally everything that came out of
Hollywood having to do with the FBI was
pro-FBI.
Right? G-Man
and uh the Untouchables and you know,
all these movies and and TV series, they
were all over the top pro FBI.
The CIA didn't start doing that until
relatively recently,
like around 9/11. They They had worked
with studios in the past, but they set
up a dedicated branch within the office
of public affairs
just to liaise with Hollywood studios so
that everything that comes out of
Hollywood that is CIA related is pro
CIA. Like Zero Dark Thirty, for example.
Zero Dark Thirty caused
so many problems
because
it perpetuated the lie
that torture led to the location of
Osama bin Laden. It did not.
Really great analysis led to the
location of Osama bin Laden.
Uh but
Kathryn Bigelow, the the director and
producer of uh Zero Dark Thirty and Mark
Boal, the writer and producer of Zero
Dark Thirty, received classified
briefings
over a classified mock-up of the bin
Laden compound.
How is that not a violation of the
Espionage Act?
Providing national defense information
to any person not entitled to receive
it. It's as simple as that.
And then in
in
repayment
every CIA analyst or operations officer
that
worked with the writer and the director
got an invitation to the to the premiere
in Hollywood. And if they couldn't make
it, they got a watch.
Okay, that's also illegal. You can't do
that. You can't accept any gift worth
more than $25.
And they did it anyway.
And then Leon Panetta
invited them to a classified
speech that he gave in the CIA
auditorium, the bubble, in which he
outed the names of the six Navy SEALs
that killed Osama bin Laden.
Later saying, "Oh, my bad. I didn't know
they were in the audience." You invited
them to the audience. How is that not a
violation of the Espionage Act?
But there's this overwhelming desire
to be made to look like the good guys
that they just want to be break the law
to get there.
>> Kind of to
pivot a little bit. So, I had a personal
question again.
I've heard you be relatively I guess
anti-monarchy, at least modern
monarchies.
I'm wondering how you square kind of
being pro-democracy with like Byzantine
symphonia and that kind of Orthodox idea
of monarchy.
>> That's a great question.
And I am a staunch, like a militant
supporter of the Byzantine Empire.
[laughter]
I admit it. I even own a Byzantine I I
own a 10th century Byzantine hand
grenade.
>> What?
>> Yeah, made out of mud in the shape of a
fish
with crosses on it.
>> Wow.
>> Uh-huh.
Uh, I bought it at a at an antiquities
auction in London.
>> [laughter]
>> That's interesting.
>> Um
back then
people weren't educated, they weren't
literate.
They they couldn't, you know, lead
themselves. There were, you know, parts
of the world that tried and anarchy
ensued and
the church was really the guiding light
back in those early centuries.
And so, yeah, I had no I had no problem
with
with Byzantium or with with royal
Constantinople after that. But I'm also
staunchly opposed to the to the
Greek royal family, which has not one
drop of Greek blood.
They're Bavarian and Danish.
Thank you very much.
>> Yeah.
>> You're welcome to stay in Bavaria and
Denmark.
And um
and
yeah, I've been taking it on the chin
lately for my opposition to the return
of the Iranian so-called royal family.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, I heard you talking about that
specifically in in a podcast the your
opposition to it. Um
where does that like opposition to
monarchy stem from? I guess monarchy in
the modern world are we too far advanced
for maybe monarchy now and democracy is
the best form of government?
>> I I think so.
>> Okay. Kind of touched on this in the
beginning a little bit, but the idea
that your spirituality played a big part
in um your time at the CIA and you
mentioned something in your in a
previous podcast you said we thought we
were the good guys.
>> Yes.
>> Right?
Did Did your faith play a role in that
idea and like
>> Absolutely yes.
>> Okay.
>> Absolutely positively yes.
>> Elaborate on that.
>> Either we're going to live
according to the principles that we
profess to live by
or we're not.
I say this all the time. Ronald Reagan
said in the 1984 Republican Convention
that the United States was a shining
city on a hill.
We were a beacon of hope for human
rights and civil rights and civil
liberties.
But we're not.
>> Mhm.
>> We like to tell people we are. We say it
all the time.
In 1977 Congress mandated
that the State Department produce every
year a human rights report for every
country on Earth with which we have
diplomatic relations. I was the human
rights officer both in Kuwait and in
Bahrain.
I took it very seriously.
And so
as an example, it's an example I use all
the time. I once had to go to the
Minister of Interior and say, "Your
Highness, you cannot
beat to death a 15-year-old child
because he marched in a pro-democracy
demonstration.
I have to report that to Congress and
it's going to jeopardize your weapons
purchases.
You got to stop doing that. You can't
just beat people to death because you
don't like their politics.
But then I say, what happens then when
hypothetically speaking, the CIA station
chief goes in and says,
"Don't listen to the human rights guy.
We'll give you $10 million.
If you set up a torture chamber
and you torture people for us and then
you just give us a transcript of what
they say."
You know, are we going to be the good
guys?
Or are we not going to be the good guys?
Are we going to be the shining city on
the hill?
Or are we going to be the country that
runs torture chambers and and
secret prisons and does international
secret kidnappings and sends out
assassination squads? Cuz we can't be
both.
>> You you can't be both. You have you
can't be
lukewarm, right? You have to be hot or
cold. Um, choose one and I'm assuming
that
orthodoxy and the Orthodox faith played
a
huge role in your decision to
whistleblow at the end of the segment.
>> really did.
>> Okay.
>> I say all the time, too, that at the CIA
the culture is such that they want you
to think that everything is a shade of
gray,
right? And that's just not true. Some
things are black and white. They're
either right or wrong.
And so,
we should do what's right.
And if you don't like the law, let's say
you and I
disagree about torture
and you want to torture.
Okay, knock yourself out, but you have
to change the law
because the law is clear. You can't just
pretend that the law doesn't apply to
you or pretend that the law doesn't
exist
or pretend that the law says exactly the
opposite of what it actually says in
black and white. That's just not
real life.
>> Now,
John, we have our final few segments
here in the show. Thank you again for
all your answers. They've been
spectacular.
>> My pleasure.
>> Um,
I would say at the end of our show we we
like to conclude with a quick fire
segment. I think it gives us the
opportunity gives you the opportunity to
kind of just say the first thing that
comes to your mind, right? So for the
first question um
I'm going to say
a list of names and you're going to tell
me the first thing that comes to your
mind. Vladimir Putin.
>> [laughter]
>> Baptized.
>> Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> Donald Trump.
>> Confused.
>> George W. Bush.
>> Clueless.
>> Benjamin Netanyahu.
>> The Antichrist.
>> Tucker Carlson.
>> One of the sweetest, most genuine men
I've ever met in my life.
>> And finally Piers Morgan.
>> Respect.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
I like and respect Piers.
>> Good.
Who would you hand pick as the next
president if you could?
>> Tucker Carlson.
I really would. Tucker and I disagree on
a lot of issues, but I've come to know
the guy very well and he is as honest as
the day is long.
>> In preparing for this interview we
actually were practicing this question
and he assumed you would say that, which
was funny. Um
>> I spoke to him a couple of weeks ago and
I said I said
I always tell him he should run for
president. And he's like, "No, no, no.
No, I'm not interested." And then I went
up there the other day and I said
I I'd spoken to a mutual friend
and I know that the mutual friend had
told him you you have to run for
president. So I said to him, "Listen, I
know I say it all the time and I know
you heard it from
our friend the other day,
but you have to run for president."
And much to my shock, he said
"I have no plans to run for president."
And I was like,
"Yes! The non-denial denial."
>> [laughter]